<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding Text as a Nexus of Perspective Hierarchies: Case Studies in XML, LMNL, and RDF</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>William Michael</forename>
                  <surname>Broughton</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                  <forename>Claudia</forename>
                  <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" xml:id="vany">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                  <forename>Tanja</forename>
                  <surname>Wissik</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt><resp>Encoded by </resp><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
               <forename>Vanessa</forename>
               <surname>Hannesschläger</surname> and  
            </persName></respStmt><respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/249676043" xml:id="dani">
                  <forename>Daniel</forename>
                  <surname>Schopper</surname>
               </persName></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
            <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-11-08">8 November 2016</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" notBefore="2016-08-02">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies to this text.</p>
                  <p>The license was added for the print version of this text on August 2, 2016.</p>
                  <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Encoding Text as a Nexus of Perspective Hierarchies: Case Studies in XML, LMNL, and RDF</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>William Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Broughton</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author></analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                     <forename>Claudia</forename>
                     <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                        <forename>Tanja</forename>
                        <surname>Wissik</surname>
                     </persName></editor>
                  <respStmt><resp>Layout and Graphic Design </resp><persName><forename>Sandra</forename> <surname>Lehecka</surname></persName></respStmt>
                  <title>TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting 2016. Book of Abstracts</title>
               <idno type="ISBN">978-3-200-04689-4</idno>
                  <imprint><publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2016-09-20">September 2016</date>
                  </imprint><biblScope unit="page">57-58</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listEvent>
               <event when="2016-05-15" type="submission"><desc>Submitted for review by the author.</desc></event>
               <event when="2016-07-25" type="finalUpload"><desc>Submitted for publication by the author.</desc></event></listEvent>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><quotation><p>The <gi>q</gi> element was used to represent all quotationmarks.</p></quotation><p>Where necessary, the abstracts were revised to American spelling during the editorial process.</p></editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass><keywords>
         <term>paper</term>
      </keywords>
         <keywords><term>XML</term><term>RDF</term><term>LMNL</term><term>OHCO</term><term>standoff</term><term>modelling</term><term>chicken</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange><change when="2016-11-04" who="#dani">Converted from InDesign (XML export to TEI P5).</change>
            <change when="2016-11-08" who="#vany">TEIHeader edited, encoding of text.</change><change when="2017-01-18" who="#vany">Keywords added.</change></listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>It is a fairly easy thing to challenge long standing best practices, especially in a
            field as increasingly sophisticated as ours is; it is an altogether more difficult
            thing, however, to actually put that audacious theorizing into practice. I have
            previously advanced the argument that many of the ills facing the encoding of textual
            resources are due less to the technical limitations of our practice, but rather to the
            model of text which underpins it. Instead, I suggest a model of text which extends the
            (often bemoaned, though still influential) OHCO model, envisioning text not as a single
            structured hierarchy of content object, but rather as a multidimensional matrix of
            sometimes conflicting, but ultimately interrelated, hierarchies of values. Modeling text
            – and encoding it – thus would, I argued, allow for nearly seamless data interchange and
            interoperability, and also for the simultaneous encoding of divergent interpretation
            within a single interpretative hierarchy – the encoding of dissensus – within a single
            resource.</p>
         <p>However, the time has come to put this theory into practice. What would a text encoded
            in this way look like? How would it operate? And could any existing encoding scheme or
            language stand up to the demands I require of it? To answer these questions, I have
            encoded a single textual source (Doug Zonker’s <q>Chicken Chicken Chicken: Chicken
            Chicken</q>) using a layered, dimensional approach using three separate encoding languages:
            TEI-flavored XML, the Layered Markup and Annotation Language (LMNL), and the Resource
            Description Framework (RDF), serialized as JSON-LD. While each of the encoding schemes
            offers unique benefits to the problem, they bring many and varied challenges as well.
            But both the benefits and the challenges provide valuable insight into the work of
            reconsidering text as more than the one thing, or even as more than one thing at the
            same time.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>