<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>STEP Transcriptor and STEP Text Comparator</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>André</forename>
                  <surname>De Tienne</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                  <forename>Claudia</forename>
                  <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" xml:id="vany">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                  <forename>Tanja</forename>
                  <surname>Wissik</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname> and </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/249676043" xml:id="dani">
                  <forename>Daniel</forename>
                  <surname>Schopper</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
               Sciences</publisher>
            <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2017-01-23">23 January 2017</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" notBefore="2016-08-02">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies
                     to this text.</p>
                  <p>The license was added for the print version of this text on August 2, 2016.</p>
                  <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>STEP Transcriptor and STEP Text Comparator</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>André</forename>
                        <surname>De Tienne</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                        <forename>Claudia</forename>
                        <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                        <forename>Tanja</forename>
                        <surname>Wissik</surname>
                     </persName></editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Layout and Graphic Design </resp>
                     <persName><forename>Sandra</forename>
                        <surname>Lehecka</surname></persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <title>TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting 2016. Book of Abstracts</title>
               <idno type="ISBN">978-3-200-04689-4</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
                        Sciences</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2016-09-20">September 2016</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">123-124</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listEvent>
               <event when="2016-05-15" type="submission">
                  <desc>Submitted for review by the author.</desc>
               </event>
               <event when="2016-07-19" type="finalUpload">
                  <desc>Submitted for publication by the author.</desc>
               </event>
            </listEvent>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation><p>The <gi>q</gi> element was used to represent all quotationmarks.</p></quotation>
            <p>Where necessary, the abstracts were revised to American spelling during the editorial process.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass><keywords>
         <term>poster</term>
      </keywords>
         <keywords><term>STEP Transcriptor</term><term>STEP Text Comparator</term><term>text comparison</term><term>transcription</term><term>apparatus lists</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2016-11-04" who="#dani">Converted from InDesign (XML export to TEI
               P5).</change>
            <change when="2016-11-23" who="#vany">TEIHeader edited, encoding of text.</change>
         <change when="2017-01-18" who="#vany">Keywords added.</change></listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>STEP Transcriptor and STEP Text Comparator are two of several tools being developed to
            accompany the online Scholarly Text Editing Platform, a general solution that provides a
            complete transcription, editing, annotation, and layout workflow for scholarly editing
            projects. STEP Transcriptor has been designed and engineered to help transcribers encode
            complex texts easily while complying with TEI’s manuscript transcription encoding
            principles. The app (for Mac and Windows) takes care of nearly all of the tedious
            aspects of TEI encoding. It provides five distinct encoding methods (via pull-down
            menus, pop-up menus, function keys, keyboard shortcuts, and specialized tagging cursors)
            that help insert tags, attributes, and values accurately while minimizing typing.
            Several specialized widgets automatically take care of especially complex encoding
            situations (including nested alterations and transpositions). STEP Transcriptor
            automatically creates lists of well-described alterations. It also provides a separate
            field to enter all sorts of descriptive tags, separately from transcriptive tags.
            Everything about the app is customizable: the content of menus, the selection of TEI
            tags, attributes, and values, even tag colors.</p>
         <p>STEP Text Comparator is a less ambitious but equally handy tool. It allows editors to
            compare two versions of a same text at a time, whether variant texts of a same author,
            or a perfected transcription with its scholarly-edited variant, or a text with and
            without alterations. The comparison is done paragraph by paragraph, sentence by
            sentence, sentence segment by segment, and word by word. The software outputs a complete
            report about all variations (sorted by categories) and automatically creates editable
            apparatus lists usable for distinct purposes (lists of emendations, of rejected
            substantives, of alterations) in normal or TEI-XML form.</p>
         <p>The poster presentation will display the key functionalities of each software.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>