<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Andreas Okopenko: diaries from the poet’s estate (hybrid edition)</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Desiree</forename>
                  <surname>Hebenstreit</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Arno</forename>
                  <surname>Herberth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100576375">
                  <forename>Laura</forename>
                  <surname>Tezarek</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/296142770">
                  <forename>Christian</forename>
                  <surname>Zolles</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                  <forename>Claudia</forename>
                  <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" xml:id="vany">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                  <forename>Tanja</forename>
                  <surname>Wissik</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname> and </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/249676043" xml:id="dani">
                  <forename>Daniel</forename>
                  <surname>Schopper</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
               Sciences</publisher>
            <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2017-01-23">23 January 2017</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" notBefore="2016-08-02">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies
                     to this text.</p>
                  <p>The license was added for the print version of this text on August 2, 2016.</p>
                  <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>Andreas Okopenko: diaries from the poet’s estate (hybrid edition)</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Desiree</forename>
                        <surname>Hebenstreit</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Arno</forename>
                        <surname>Herberth</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/100576375">
                        <forename>Laura</forename>
                        <surname>Tezarek</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/296142770">
                        <forename>Christian</forename>
                        <surname>Zolles</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                        <forename>Claudia</forename>
                        <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                        <forename>Tanja</forename>
                        <surname>Wissik</surname>
                     </persName></editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Layout and Graphic Design </resp>
                     <persName><forename>Sandra</forename>
                        <surname>Lehecka</surname></persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <title>TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting 2016. Book of Abstracts</title>
               <idno type="ISBN">978-3-200-04689-4</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
                        Sciences</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2016-09-20">September 2016</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">131-132</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listEvent>
               <event when="2016-05-13" type="submission">
                  <desc>Submitted for review by the authors.</desc>
               </event>
               <event when="2016-08-01" type="consent">
                  <desc>Consent to publication by the authors.</desc>
               </event>
            </listEvent>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation><p>The <gi>q</gi> element was used to represent all quotationmarks.</p></quotation>
            <p>Where necessary, the abstracts were revised to American spelling during the editorial process.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass><keywords>
         <term>poster</term>
      </keywords>
         <keywords><term>Austrian avantgarde</term><term>literary legacy</term><term>diaries</term><term>hybrid edition</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2016-11-04" who="#dani">Converted from InDesign (XML export to TEI
               P5).</change>
            <change when="2016-11-23" who="#vany">TEIHeader edited, encoding of text.</change>
         <change when="2017-01-18" who="#vany">Keywords added.</change></listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>In the year 2012, the Literary Archives of the Austrian National Library acquired the
            rights to the literary estate of the Austrian poet Andreas Okopenko (1930-2010), winner,
            among others, of the Grand Austrian State Prize for Literature (1998) and the Georg
            Trakl Prize (2002). His estate is a comprehensive collection of diary notations,
            typescripts, notes, correspondence, and other material. It has been partly arranged by
            the poet himself, and its classification has been informally continued by the Literary
            Archives. Regarding text-genetical (1.), poetological (2.) and literary historical (3.)
            aspects, the diaries are the core of the 28 boxes of the poet’s estate (which has to be
            matched with the 25 boxes of the pre mortem bequest).</p>
         <p>Throughout his life, Andreas Okopenko kept a position outside of all existing literary
            trends. This means that the estate is important in at least three ways: It allows us to
            compare his personal writings with the typescripts and text variants and to lay the
            foundations for a comprehensive text-genetical study and interpretation for Okopenko’s
            experimental work – ranging from literary small forms to essays and radio plays, up to
            his best known avant-gardist novels Lexikon-Roman (1970) and Kindernazi (1984) (1.).
            Furthermore, Okopenko’s writing is characterized by providing a feeling of <q>personal</q>
            realism (Concretionism) and by a high level of cultural self-reflection. As such, the
            estate stands as a formidable individualistic testimony of contemporary Austrian history
            (2.). Finally, Okopenko turned out to be a reserved but rigorous observer of the
            literary scene in Austria’s Second Republic. Therefore, the diaries in particular will
            provide different views on the formation and the local value of Austrian literature
            (3.). The first-range importance of the literary estate as a whole can be found in the
            areas of text-genetical and interpretational research and in literary and contemporary
            history. Okopenko’s highly personal perceptions and awareness of his own historical
            context make him a distinguished <q>archaeologist</q>, <q>archivist</q> and <q>chronicler</q> of his
            time.</p>
         <p>Above all, the first-range importance of the literary estate can be found in the area of
            Digital Humanities. Regarding Okopenko’s pioneer work in hypertext-poetry, the project
            will focus on an annotated digital edition of the diaries (following the TEI Guidelines)
            connected to the website of the Austrian National Library in a sustainable manner and
            with unlimited access. In addition, the most significant parts of the annotated diaries
            will be printed. A close collaboration between the Department for German Studies of the
            University of Vienna (Univ.-Prof. Dr. Roland Innerhofer) and the Literary Archives
            (Priv.-Doz. Dr. Bernhard Fetz) will guarantee the optimal valorization of the estate and
            will represent Okopenko’s writing in a contemporary light.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>