<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>eXistdb: more than a database</title>
            <author>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/307490314">
                  <forename>Magdalena</forename>
                  <surname>Turska</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Lars</forename>
                  <surname>Windauer</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                  <forename>Claudia</forename>
                  <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" xml:id="vany">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                  <forename>Tanja</forename>
                  <surname>Wissik</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname> and </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/249676043" xml:id="dani">
                  <forename>Daniel</forename>
                  <surname>Schopper</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
               Sciences</publisher>
            <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2017-01-23">23 January 2017</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" notBefore="2016-08-02">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies
                     to this text.</p>
                  <p>The license was added for the print version of this text on August 2, 2016.</p>
                  <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>eXistdb: more than a database</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/307490314">
                        <forename>Magdalena</forename>
                        <surname>Turska</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Lars</forename>
                        <surname>Windauer</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                        <forename>Claudia</forename>
                        <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                        <forename>Tanja</forename>
                        <surname>Wissik</surname>
                     </persName></editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>Layout and Graphic Design </resp>
                     <persName><forename>Sandra</forename>
                        <surname>Lehecka</surname></persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <title>TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting 2016. Book of Abstracts</title>
               <idno type="ISBN">978-3-200-04689-4</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of
                        Sciences</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2016-09-20">September 2016</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">185-186</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listEvent>
               <event when="2016-07-25" type="submission">
                  <desc>Submitted for review by the authors.</desc>
               </event>
               <event when="2016-08-11" type="finalUpload">
                  <desc>Submitted for publication by the authors.</desc>
               </event>
            </listEvent>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation><p>The <gi>q</gi> element was used to represent all quotationmarks.</p></quotation>
            <p>Where necessary, the abstracts were revised to American spelling during the editorial process.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass>
         <keywords>
            <term>workshop</term>
         </keywords>
         <keywords><term>existdb</term><term>tei publishing</term><term>TEI-Simple</term><term>TEI-Processing Model</term></keywords>
      </textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2016-11-04" who="#dani">Converted from InDesign (XML export to TEI
               P5).</change>
            <change when="2017-01-05" who="#vany">TEIHeader edited, encoding of text.</change>
         <change when="2017-01-18" who="#vany">Keywords added.</change></listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Day 1: Crash course in eXistdb basics for TEI data</head>
            <head>Day 2: X‐wiZZardry: application building with eXistdb</head>
         <p>A significant portion of humanities research data is marked up and stored as XML
            documents. In order to provide standard interactive features for digital research
            resources such as full text search possibilities, it is obvious to use a database which
            is optimized for the handling of XML documents. eXistdb is one of the leading native XML
            databases currently available. This open source solution is becoming a technology of
            choice in Digital Humanities, especially when it comes to storing, querying and
            publishing large corpora of XML marked-up texts. eXistdb though is much more than just a
            database: It is also an application platform, web server and even a document creation
            platform. eXistdb is also currently the only out‐of‐the‐box implementation of the TEI
            Processing Model. Thus, it is extremely well suited to be a database, rapid application
            development and publishing solution of choice for large, established collaborative
            projects and individual researchers alike.</p>
         <p>This tutorial aims for a mix of talks and hands‐on practical sessions. It will be
            divided in two parts, lasting a day each, which can be taken independently. Part one
            will provide a basic introduction to eXistdb and follow on to querying data collections
            with XPath, to conclude with publishing TEI documents with the TEI Processing Model.</p>
         <p>Part two will move beyond out‐of‐the‐box solutions and will discuss XQuery, a language
            which is used to query, extract, and manipulate XML documents as well as build
            applications for eXistdb. We will also introduce the principles of eXistdb indexing and
            profiling features. As a source of inspiration and a panorama of applications that could
            benefit from relying on eXistdb as its core technology, we will also showcase a few
            research projects using eXistdb.</p>
         <p>As eXistdb is fully based upon Open Standards and Open Source, it is a future‐proof and
            sustainable choice for research projects. Since its inception in 2001, eXistdb
            development has always been driven by the needs of a large user community. We believe
            that the TEI conference is a good opportunity for scholars to meet eXistdb contributors
            and practitioners, and to exchange ideas how the Digital Humanities community could both
            engage and benefit further from eXistdb development.</p>
         <p>The introduction to the features of eXistdb during the workshop will give participants a
            starting point for their own eXistdb‐based project as well as help them narrow their
            choices when it comes to selecting database technology suitable for their research.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>