<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI in the Archives: Unfolding the Bookshops in Paul’s Cross Churchyard</title>
            <author>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Mary Erica</forename>
                  <surname>Zimmer</surname>
               </persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                  <forename>Claudia</forename>
                  <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230" xml:id="vany">
                  <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                  <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                  <forename>Tanja</forename>
                  <surname>Wissik</surname>
               </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt><resp>Encoded by </resp><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
               <forename>Vanessa</forename>
               <surname>Hannesschläger</surname> and  
            </persName></respStmt><respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/249676043" xml:id="dani">
                  <forename>Daniel</forename>
                  <surname>Schopper</surname>
               </persName></respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
            <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2017-01-23">23 January 2017</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" notBefore="2016-08-02">
                  <p>The Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) License applies to this text.</p>
                  <p>The license was added for the print version of this text on August 2, 2016.</p>
                  <p>The CC BY 4.0 License also applies to this TEI XML file.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title>TEI in the Archives: Unfolding the Bookshops in Paul’s Cross Churchyard</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mary Erica</forename>
                        <surname>Zimmer</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author></analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/52846347">
                     <forename>Claudia</forename>
                     <surname>Resch</surname></persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/31146030596135862230">
                        <forename>Vanessa</forename>
                        <surname>Hannesschläger</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/70107717">
                        <forename>Tanja</forename>
                        <surname>Wissik</surname>
                     </persName></editor>
                  <respStmt><resp>Layout and Graphic Design </resp><persName><forename>Sandra</forename> <surname>Lehecka</surname></persName></respStmt>
                  <title>TEI Conference and Members’ Meeting 2016. Book of Abstracts</title>
               <idno type="ISBN">978-3-200-04689-4</idno>
                  <imprint><publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Austrian Academy of Sciences</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4066009-6">Vienna</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2016-09-20">September 2016</date>
                  </imprint><biblScope unit="page">157-158</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listEvent>
               <event when="2016-05-31" type="submission"><desc>Submitted for review by the author.</desc></event>
               <event when="2016-07-31" type="finalUpload"><desc>Submitted for publication by the author.</desc></event></listEvent>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><quotation><p>The <gi>q</gi> element was used to represent all quotationmarks.</p></quotation><p>Where necessary, the abstracts were revised to American spelling during the editorial process.</p></editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass><keywords>
         <term>poster</term>
      </keywords>
         <keywords><term>TEI</term><term>archives</term><term>digitization</term><term>corpora</term><term>search</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange><change when="2016-11-04" who="#dani">Converted from InDesign (XML export to TEI P5).</change>
            <change when="2016-12-19" who="#vany">TEIHeader edited, encoding of text.</change><change when="2017-01-18" who="#vany">Keywords added.</change></listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Writing in 2000 of <q>[d]igital archives combined with new technologies,</q> Seamus Ross
            lauded this union’s ability to support <q>simultaneous access to a range of sources</q> as
            well as development of <q>research methods not possible with […] printed or hand written
            records</q> alone. Less frequently discussed, however, are ways digital connections may
            enrich understanding of print and manuscript records themselves, while encouraging
            scholarship that draws upon both. Recent projects such as Shakespeare Documented show
            digitized archives’ potential not only for reuniting fragmented artifacts, but also for
            evolving new, composite wholes to support research.</p>
         <p>Such potential extends as well to encouraging engagement with existing scholarship.
            Among salient examples potentially complemented by an approach of this kind would be the
            landmark work of Peter W. M. Blayney, whose 1990 The Bookshops in Paul’s Cross
            Churchyard uses meticulous archival research to map the evolving footprint of the shops
            and their inhabitants. Resulting has been a powerful print visualization: a composite,
            layered image of shops, their locations, and their inhabitants. Centrally, this project
            proposes to create a digitized model of the context Blayney has rendered, while
            connecting aspects of the reconstruction to the documents used to create it. Making the
            research’s archival foundations visible honors the initial, seminal achievement while
            encouraging exploration – and emulation – of the work.</p>
         <p>The proposed project’s TEI encoding of key documents will observe existing permissions
            while developing a composite resource. Connecting print and manuscript archives through
            a third medium will provide perspective on ways early modern records may present
            reciprocal and reinforcing information. Intersections with further early modern corpora
            also appear promising, particularly given the January 2015 release of over 25,000
            TEI-compliant SGML-encoded EEBO-TCP texts. Ultimately, TEI’s role as a common language
            remains vital to the project’s success.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>